<section id="amavisd-new">
    <title>Scanning with <literal>amavisd-new</literal></title>

    <para><literal>amavisd-new</literal> operates as an SMTP proxy, designed
    to hook in to the <literal>content_filter</literal> mechanism of Postfix.
    (<literal>amavisd-new</literal> also supports Sendmail through its Milter
    interface and in a dual-server configuration and Exim using it as an
    SMTP proxy.)  <literal>amavisd-new</literal> is written, maintained,
    and supported by Mark Martinec of the Jozef Stefan Institue in Slovenija
    and is aided by an active user community.  It began as a fork from
    <literal>amavisd</literal>, a daemonized version of the AMaViS scanner,
    which was one of the first open source mail virus scanners.  The modern
    <literal>amavisd-new</literal> scarcely resemebles its predecessor and
    improves upon it considerably, while a difference of philosophies has
    prevented <literal>amavisd-new</literal> from being merged back into
    <literal>amavisd</literal> or simply taking over as the official scanning
    engine of the AMaViS project.  That should not sound like a euphemism
    for saying that either Mark or the developers of the original AMaViS have
    overbearing personalities; Mark himself is helpful and personable on the
    amavis-users mailing list, and the original AMaViS folks have been quite
    tolerant of the <literal>amavisd-new</literal> traffic on their list,
    which these days accounts for at least half.  </para>

    <para><literal>amavisd-new</literal> is written in Perl, and takes
    advantage of a number of Perl modules, such as the Net::Server module,
    which it uses to implement a robust forked parent/child environment,
    and Mail::SpamAssassin, the core scanning engine of SpamAssassin, so it
    does not need to use 'spamd'.</para>

    <para>Mark strives to make <literal>amavisd-new</literal> adhere to
    standards and as the result is a well-regarded and standards-friendly
    system.  It is also fast, although as a Perl application it can use a
    considerable amount of memory, so it is best limited to a few child
    processes.  As <literal>amavisd-new</literal> is very flexible, the
    myriad of options makes it intimidating to configure.</para>

    <para><literal>amavisd-new</literal> is able to reliably deliver
    messages because it never has to store the messages itself; as soon as
    the Postfix sending process connects to <literal>amavisd-new</literal>,
    <literal>amavisd-new</literal> connects to the Postfix receiving process
    and does not send an acceptance response to the sending process until the
    receiving process has also accepted the message.  Should the receiving
    process fail, <literal>amavisd-new</literal> will return a status code
    to the Postfix sending process and Postfix will maintain the message in
    its queue until the problem is rectified.</para>

</section>

<!-- vim:ft=docbkxml
-->
