<section id="postfix">

    <title>Understanding the Postfix <literal>content_filter</literal>
    Mechanism</title>

    <para>The Postfix mail transfer agent (MTA) provides
    <literal>content_filter</literal>, a flexible mechanism designed to
    allow the integration of arbitrary mail filters through a well-defined
    interface.  Postfix passes the message into the content filter at the
    queuing stage, which in the diagrams in the Postfix documentation is
    labelled <literal>qmgr</literal>, which is the name of the internal
    process that maintains queues for incoming and outgoing messages.</para>

    <para>The simplest of the <literal>content_filter</literal> interfaces
    is a UNIX pipe, where Postfix writes to the filter's standard input
    and checks the filter's return value for pre-defined status codes.
    Mail is injected back into Postfix using the <literal>sendmail</literal>
    command, which is the Postfix replacement for the same Sendmail command.
    The example in the <literal>FILTER_README</literal> document that ships
    with Postfix uses <literal>cat</literal> and acts as a simple pass-through
    filter.</para>

    <para>The best interface for sophisticated mail filtering is not the
    pipe mechanism, but rather the SMTP proxy mechanism.  This provides
    a well-defined interface between Postfix and the filter and allows
    a persistent scanning daemon, which reduces overhead and allows the
    filtering proxy to deliver reliably.  Because the SMTP proxy mechanism
    operates over TCP/IP, the content filter can be located on a separate
    host than the Postfix service that receives the mail.</para>

    <para>The <literal>content_filter</literal> requires Postfix to connect
    to the proxy as an SMTP client, which handles the message and then
    connects back into a special SMTP server which handles the final routing
    and delivery of the message.  As mentioned before, Postfix sends the
    message to the content filter at the queuing stage; this will be called
    the "sending process"; the message is re-injected into the Postfix
    system in the <literal>smtpd</literal> stage, which will be called the
    "receiving process."</para>

</section>

<!-- vim:ft=docbkxml
-->
